<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recipes on skovati</title>
    <link>https://skovati.dev/recipes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recipes on skovati</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 18:00:06 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://skovati.dev/recipes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Caramel</title>
      <link>https://skovati.dev/recipes/caramel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 18:00:06 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://skovati.dev/recipes/caramel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;soft-chewy-salted-caramels&#34;&gt;Soft, Chewy, Salted Caramels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dangerously easy to make soft caramel candies. Read through the whole recipe before starting so you&amp;rsquo;re comfortable with the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup (113 g) unsalted butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup (120 ml) heavy whipping cream&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup (60 ml) light corn syrup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 cup (200 grams) sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon course or flaked sea salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;preparing-the-pan&#34;&gt;Preparing the pan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to do this step early, as things will be moving quick down the line. I like to use a bread loaf pan to cool my caramels in. Take a sheet of parchment paper and line the bottom and sides of a loaf pan. Then, take a small amount of vegetable oil and spread it on the parchment paper—gotta make sure they don&amp;rsquo;t stick! Set this pan aside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heating-the-sugar-solution&#34;&gt;Heating the sugar solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a small saucepan, combine the water, corn syrup, and sugar. When pouring the sugar in, aim for the middle, and try not to get any sugar crystals on the side of the pan. Use a spatula to gently combine the water and sugar until everything is hydrated. Heat this over medium heat until the sugar solution comes to a boil. Once boiling, cover the pan with its lid for a minute or so—this is to create some condensation in the pan which helps any sugar stuck on the side of the pan fall down into the boiling mixture. If you have too much sugar on the sides of the pan, this can cause a gritty texture in your final product. Remove the lid and place a candy thermometer in the pan. Cook for 5-10 minutes until the solution reaches 320° F. While the solution is cooking, cut your stick of butter into chunks and place in a microwave safe glass measure cup. Add the heavy whipping cream, and microwave this solution for a minute or two until the butter has melted. Set this aside for the next step. As soon as the sugar reaches 320° F, start the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;adding-the-butter-cream&#34;&gt;Adding the butter cream&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the sugar reaches 320° F, add about 1/6th of the butter cream solution and start mixing it in with the base of the candy thermometer. Repeat this several times until all the cream has been incorporated. The sugar solution will bubble violently while this is happening, don&amp;rsquo;t worry, just keep adding the solution to bring the temperature down. After all the cream has been mixed in, heat this solution for another few minutes until it reaches 240° F. This will create a soft caramel—if you want slightly harder caramels, heat a few more degrees, but no hotter than 245° F. As soon as the solution reaches your desired temperature, take it off the heat and pour it into the prepared loaf pan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;letting-it-cool&#34;&gt;Letting it cool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t touch this for at least 20-30 minutes. Then sprinkle your sea salt on top. Let sit for another 1-3 hours—really as long as you can manage. Then, lift the parchment paper out of the pan, and set the caramels on a cutting board. Spray a sharp knife with cooking spray, and then cut into small cubes. Wrap with or place on parchment paper and store in an airtight container or the fridge for best longevity. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pizza</title>
      <link>https://skovati.dev/recipes/pizza/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 18:00:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://skovati.dev/recipes/pizza/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;simple-pizza-recipe&#34;&gt;Simple Pizza Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/4 teaspoon active dry yeast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup warm water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1-1.5 cups flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;oregano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/3 cup canned pureed tomatoes or pasta sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh basil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 ounces whole milk mozzarella&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;any other toppings you want (garlic, onions, peppers, meat)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-dough&#34;&gt;The Dough&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mix the yeast, sugar, and water together in a bowl and let sit for 5-10 minutes. I like to wait until I can smell the yeast to make sure it&amp;rsquo;s active and happy. Put in one cup of flour and the salt, and start kneading with your hands. Keep adding flour as needed to keep the dough from being too sticky, but don&amp;rsquo;t add too much! Knead until the dough passes the &amp;ldquo;window pane test&amp;rdquo; where you stretch it out carefully and check to see if you can see light through it without it ripping. When ready, place in a small bowl with olive oil and cover with cloth and let rise—at least 24 hours in the fridge, or 1-2 hours at room temp, until size has increased and the dough is very soft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 10 inch cast iron pan, drizzle a little olive oil. You don&amp;rsquo;t need much—the dough is already oiled. Put in some oregano, black pepper, salt, and optionally some cornmeal. Spread that mixture around the pan. Grab the dough and rotate it slowly so it falls into a circular shape. Place and fit into the pan, and let proof another 20 minutes or so as you get the toppings ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-sauce&#34;&gt;The Sauce&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, I&amp;rsquo;m lazy, and I just end up using some store bought pasta sauce. I think this works totally fine, but if you want to get fancy you can use those purred tomatoes (or blend your own), and combine them with some olive oil and chopped basil leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cooking-the-pizza&#34;&gt;Cooking the Pizza&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main methods I go between when cooking these: if the oven can get pretty hot, around 550+° F, I usually just max out the oven and bake it in the pan anywhere from 10-15 minutes, checking on it every couple minutes to make sure the crust is baking nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, if your oven doesn&amp;rsquo;t get too hot, or you really want a crispy crust on the bottom, you can cook it on the stove and then broil it to finish. Turn a burner on medium and the broiler on high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dressing-the-pizza&#34;&gt;Dressing the Pizza&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on which cooking method you want to use, you&amp;rsquo;ll either add all the toppings at once or at different times. Regardless of which method you use, you&amp;rsquo;ll want to saute toppings like onions or peppers for a few minutes to make sure they&amp;rsquo;re fully cooked at the end. If baking in the oven, saute your toppings and then spread the sauce, toppings, and cheese on top of the pizza and throw it in the oven. If cooking on the stove, add the sauce right away, and cook on medium for around 7-8 minutes, until the dough starts bubbling underneath. Then, add the rest of your toppings now, making sure the cheese is as cold as possible. Then, throw under the broiler for 4-5 minutes, or to your liking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-thats-it&#34;&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s it!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your preferred cooking method is done, take the pan out and let it cool for several minutes. If you used enough oil the pizza shouldn&amp;rsquo;t stick at all. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pancakes</title>
      <link>https://skovati.dev/recipes/pancakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 17:59:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://skovati.dev/recipes/pancakes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;simple-pancake-recipe&#34;&gt;Simple Pancake Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a simple, effective recipe for a simple, effective food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;28 g butter (2 tbsp)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25 g sugar (2 tbsp)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 ml vanilla extract (2 tsp)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;400 ml milk (1 &amp;amp; 3/4 cup)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 g salt (1 tsp)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16 g baking powder (1.25 tbsp)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200-300 g flour (1.5-2.5 cups)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-batter&#34;&gt;The Batter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melt the butter without it getting too hot, I like to use a microwave safe glass measuring cup. Mix in the sugar and beat the egg into the butter thoroughly, I just use a fork. Mix in the vanilla, milk, salt, and baking powder. Start mixing in a small portion of the flour, adding more until you reach a desired consistency. Don&amp;rsquo;t over-mix, the batter should be thick and lumpy. Batter should fall from the fork easily, but not too easily. The thicker the batter, the thicker the pancake, so don&amp;rsquo;t worry too much about the consistency—you&amp;rsquo;ll get a feel for it after a few attempts. Let the batter rest in order to hydrate the flour while you heat up your pan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cooking&#34;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heat your pan of choice—I use cast iron―to medium heat. Put butter or oil in the pan. When the butter starts to brown or the oil is glossy, pour in the batter. Look for bubbles on the edges of the cake. Take a peek at the underside and when you think it&amp;rsquo;s ready give it a flip. Doing the chef-style pan flip gives better results for large cakes, but you risk losing it all over the floor. When the cake seems done, cook for another 30 seconds to make sure, and move to a cooling plate. Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
