<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>unix on skovati</title>
    <link>https://skovati.dev/tags/unix/</link>
    <description>Recent content in unix on skovati</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 21:40:31 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://skovati.dev/tags/unix/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A minimal Vim, Markdown, and GPG powered wiki</title>
      <link>https://skovati.dev/blog/wiki/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 21:40:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://skovati.dev/blog/wiki/</guid>
      <description>Motivation and Vimwiki Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve been keeping notes, ideas, to-do lists, and journal entries in a test based wiki, thanks to the fantastic plugin vimwiki. If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar, vimwiki enables easy hyperlinking between text files marked up with either Markdown or a feature rich vimwiki syntax. This can be a collection of programming language snippets, notes from CS class, project to-do lists, a personal diary—whatever you want. You can navigate between linked files with and and even convert to HTML to view in a browser.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vim: The World&#39;s Greatest Text Editor</title>
      <link>https://skovati.dev/blog/whyvim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 20:04:39 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://skovati.dev/blog/whyvim/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: This blog post is not meant to teach Vim, (that might come later) just to act as inspiration to start the learning journey.
If you&amp;rsquo;ve been convinced by this post and want to learn Vim, here are a few fantastic tutorials that helped me get started:
 vimtutor, Vim&amp;rsquo;s built in tutorial, if Vim is installed on your system, just run vimtutor for an interactive tutorial Ben Awad&amp;rsquo;s Tutorial - watch this first, no BS, beginner to advanced DistroTube&amp;rsquo;s Vim series - moderate BS, takes it slow And for Vim-god inspiration, check out a few Luke Smith videos - dude himself is BS, but rocks at Vim And these Vim meetup talks are a good rabbit hole  Anyways&amp;hellip; the post&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
